Heat.
[Music]
Hey.
Hey. Hey.
Heat.
[Music]
Hello, good evening, good day everybody
and welcome to episode 265 of Ask
Kabjijit. Hope everybody is doing great.
Uh today once again we don't have super
chats. I'm going to take everybody's
questions as many as I can. It's going
to be a one-hour session because I had a
long uh episode of uh geo strategy that
just concluded. So let us see who all is
there on the live chat. I'll do a 1-hour
session. I'll take as many questions as
I can. I can see Daksh Aush Yadav
anonymous scientist Mojour Mwah Animish
Hitan Shua Davik Shrian Rashmi Ratur
from Rajasthan. Hello. Sujit Shanaga,
Pratam Sharma, Arian Rocking Gaming,
good evening. Meet Mistri, Barat First,
Anime, Namaste, Baba Bugatti,
Namaskaram, Hunter Canv, good evening.
Mahi Shta, Truthful Penguin, Manisha
Kardo, Anup Tead, Pranay Paul from
Kolkata. Dave Molana, Abhijit Chava,
well well from Kolinga, good to see you
sir. Uh Jimmy Watram uh Samatriati no
name Name Sergeant Skylan Animish again
Adita G uh Atman Moa Sujit Shanagunda
again Shri Namach Ramachandra Namaha Sam
the gamer Anand Chandak Jimmy Karan uh
who else we have uh Hunter Kvei uh Shah
Raj from London England Merin Sunonny
Palk
Onar Kulkarnney Utsav Katri Krishna
Ragunat from the Suriname Netherlands
Anand again Shadow Gamer Sam no name
Name Latangi Suresh Rahul Jangra
Anudipta Sin Nishant Kumar Karish
Supratim
Random Skull Mlavin Jind Nabit Tadas Bay
Nutan Roshan Geopolitical Dubai from
Indor good evening and everybody else
okay so let's take some questions let's
take some questions Truthful Penguin.
Hello. Salvatore's brother Damon is
here.
Okay, vampires. Let's go. Let's take
some questions. Oopsy. Where is the
question? Okay. Okay. Mah asks, um,
how could Iran move its nuclear
materials without the US picking up on
it considering the strong intelligence
resources they have? So we have evidence
of Maxar satellite images that show that
Iran had these convoys of trucks that
were taking materials and stuff
and equipment possibly whatever uh they
were taking these materials away from
those nuclear sites that were bombed by
the US by the B2 bombers using bunker
buster bombs. So we have satellite
images that show that this happened like
a couple of days before the bombing
happened. So it's like it's like the
Iranians knew about this, right? And Mr.
Trump had been foreshadowing his attack
on Isra on Iran for at least a couple of
weeks before it happened. And it's look,
we have no evidence that this may or may
not have happened, but it it's possible
that there could have been some
communication that something's coming
up.
So if Iran was able to move its
materials out of the nuclear sites, uh
it's not like the US did not pick up on
it. The US has eyes in the sky
everywhere. The US knows everything that
happens in real time. In real time, so
they knew it and they waited for the
materials to be taken away and then they
bombed those three sides, you know, for
the Natans and so on.
So is it a fixed match?
Is it
that's the question that is the question
unar says how can can India ever achieve
the denuclearization of Pakistan well
you see my friends most likely Pakistan
doesn't have its own indigenous nuclear
weapons most likely Pakistan has
American nuclear weapons just like the
US has parked a bunch of nuclear
warheads in Turkey a bunch in uh the
Netherlands some in some other countries
and so on. Similarly, the US seems to
have parked a bunch of nuclear warheads
in Pakistan. The objective most likely
is to counterbalance India. Right? So
that is the US approach towards India.
Please understand that. Right? So if
India is to denuclearize Pakistan, India
would have look we kind of to some
extent apparently uh
you know partially denuclearize Pakistan
with our uh strike on the Nurhan air
base. So it has now emerged that the the
Nurhan air base is operated by the US
and Pakistani military personnel are not
allowed inside. Okay. And apparently
there could have been some sensitive
materials in the Nurhan air base and our
strikes on the Nurhkan air base have
created problems there. Um,
so so
the point is that the Pakistani nuclear
arsenal is actually most likely the
American it's an American loan to
Pakistan. So to denuclearize Pakistan,
we would have to somehow convince the US
to withdraw his nuclear weapons, its
nuclear weapons from Pakistan. How to do
that is is a different story.
Um
okay, this is a good question by Pray.
What do you think was Israel's core
objective in this conflict?
Denuclearization of Iran or something
more? And has that objective been
achieved? So first of all, bottom line,
bottom line up top, Israel's objectives
have not been achieved.
Okay.
So what was the objective? Well, the
objective was Mr. Netanyahu's great
objectives. First, denuclearization of
Iran. Second, comprehensive military
defeat of Iran. Third, regime change in
Thran. Those were the objectives
of Mr. Netanyahu.
Has Iran been nucle denuclearized? It
has not been denuclearized. The US
ensured that the Iranians were able to
take out all the whatever materials and
equipment, whatever they wanted to take
out of Foro and Natans and what not,
those nuclear sites that were hit. It's
also very likely that the that the
bunker buster bombs did not destroy the
sites entirely. They must have caved in
the tunnels and the entrances to the to
the tunnels that lead into the sites.
But most likely according to US
intelligence assessments these strikes
have not destroyed the facilities
themselves. Iran will able to will be
able to eventually excavate and you know
reopen the sites the entrances to the
sites. So the deuclearization
has not happened. Iran has not been
comprehensively military defeated.
Right? It's not been a comprehensive
military defeat. Iran is claiming
victory that we have emerged victorious.
And by not being defeated, you could
claim we could you could argue that to
some extent when it comes to facing
facing up against the US and its primary
ally in the region, Iran by surviving
and by not being defeated has kind of
achieved some kind of victory. So Iran
has not been denuclearized. Iran has not
been defeated. There has been no regime
change in Iran.
So these objectives have not been met.
So what has Israel achieved?
Israel has ach assassinated some 30 40
uh top ranking Iranian IRGC leaders,
military personnel and nuclear
scientists and so on. But Iran endures.
So what else has Israel achieved? Well,
apart from that they have bombed some
facilities and so on, but no major
achievement.
no major achievement. Iran still exists.
Iran endures. Iran's nuclear program
isn't destroyed. Iran's government is
still very much in power. Uh the people
of the country have kind of rallied
around the government because of the
external threat and so on. So overall,
it's not been a victory for Israel.
Israel has not achieved its core
objectives. Israel has been thwarted.
Mr. Netanyahu has been thwarted. Mr.
Netanyahu, I don't know what he will do
now because he faces personal problems.
He faces political troubles. He faces
corruption corruption charges. A
corruption trial is ongoing.
And if for Mr. Nathan to get salvation
and freedom from this, he would have had
to achieve a comprehensive victory over
Iran. The the kind of victory that no
other Israeli leader has achieved in the
past and that has clearly not happened.
So what happens now? Mr. Nathaniel will
most likely redouble double down on the
Gaza war possibly.
So yeah, the objectives have not
been achieved.
Uh
Nimish says earlier today, NATO chief
called Donald Trump daddy live on
camera. Really?
Let me let me quickly fact check that if
if it's possible. I'm I'm astonished if
that's true. Uh, NATO chief calls Trump
daddy.
Really?
NATO chief calls Trump daddy
for using the f word in a bizarre
compliment. I have no idea what this
means. Okay, this I think is a part of
western culture I don't understand.
Okay, I don't get it. So I will What are
my thoughts? My thoughts are are that I
have no idea what what this is. I have
no idea what it means. Bizarre.
Okay. Hit Shu says, "Safon Aircraft
Engines has announced the construction
of a new MRO shop dedicated to the
Rafal's M88 engine in Hyderabad. What
are my views on further indigenous
development of future aircraft?"
They have announced the construction of
a shop dedicated to the engine of the
Rafal. It's a it's it's a factory which
will
I suppose build the engines the M88
engines. Well, I think that's a welcome
move and we should indigenize the at
least have it produced locally even if
it's produced by a French technology and
so on. Even if it's if the technology is
not transferred to us, it's a step in
the right direction. That's what I would
say. Uh this is not connected to the
indigenous further indigenous
development of future aircraft.
Jet engines are a specific niche in in a
critical niche in fighter aircraft
development. But see how does aircraft
development happen? You assume that
you're going to have an engine that
gives you a certain amount of thrust and
certain amount of performance
characteristics. You assume that and
based on that you develop the aircraft
around it. You generally develop an
aircraft around an existing engine. So
let's say you have the Rafal M8 engine.
So you develop an aircraft around it. So
you design and build an aircraft
according to these performance
characteristics of the engine or maybe
the general general electric F404 or
F414 whatever you want to take it or
maybe the future cavary engine right uh
so this doesn't really have an impact on
future indigenous development of future
aircraft
this is a good move when it comes to uh
building engines in India so I I welcome
this definitely very much
Um okay Sam Achare says dumb question.
No it's not a dumb question. How are
nuclear arsenals maintained? Well that's
that's not something we are supposed to
know. Okay. So what's a nuclear arsenal?
It's a collection of nuclear weapons.
Nuclear warheads.
A nuclear warhead is well it's an
engineering it's a mechanical device and
it has various components depending on
what kind of warhead it is whether it's
a fish device whether it's a
thermonuclear device fish fusion device
three-stage device the initial
trigger is a chemical
reaction a chemical explosion chemical
explosives yes and so on so based on the
various characteristics ics of the
nuclear weapons. You may need to open
them up for inspection and check the
various things and so on. I assume
because I have absolutely no idea, no
understanding because these things are
super secret. These things are super
secret. How do you maintain your nuclear
weapons? Do you inspect them regularly?
Do you subject them to some kind of
tests? Do you open them up and maybe
replace some components once in a while
in a in at a certain at a certain
frequency? maybe every year or maybe
every two years or whatever if required.
I'm not sure how it's done. Uh I suppose
some maintenance is done on a on a
recurring basis maybe monthly, yearly by
twice a you know once in two years or
whatever. I think it's similar to the
kind of maintenance that would typically
be done with uh with your missiles. I
mean if you have a stockpile of 10,000
missiles, you're going to have going to
have to maintain them from time to time.
uh obviously we now have solid fueled
rockets which are easier to maintain
liquid fuel rockets they have to be
fueled before uh they are launched so
that's a much more cumbersome and
complicated uh challenge so I suppose so
when it comes to your missile arsenal
you test missiles once or twice a year
you know randomly you pick some missiles
a couple of missiles and you test them
that gives you an indicator of how well
the missiles are performing and how well
they are um lasting and what is the
effect of time on them. Sometimes you'll
find that that a missile will fizzle
out. You know sometimes you may find
that so similarly some some such
maintenance will be done on nuclear
weapons but the exact specifics and
details are highly
classified and secret.
Okay.
Shah Raj says China, Pakistan, America
are allies in common issues, I believe.
Well, they're allies when it comes to
India because the US and China see eye
to eye when it comes to India. Neither
nation wants India to to grow too much,
to rise too much, right? Uh that is a
common u
point of understanding when it comes to
the US and China. But how to approach
India, there is a difference in that. So
both nations are investing in Pakistan.
Um it's something we can discuss you
know in detail in a future geost
strategy perhaps episode as to what is
the is there no conflict of interest
when it comes to China and the US in
their um relationship with Pakistan
because the US has most likely deployed
nuclear weapons in Pakistan. The US has
given has sold F-16s to Pakistan. The US
has significant investments in Pakistan
of various kinds. The US operates the
Nurhan air base. Right? So there is a
significant US presence in Pakistan. But
on the other hand, the Chinese are
selling fighter planes to Pakistan,
maybe the J35. If they sell the J35,
will the US not get get their hands on
the J35? Will there not be a problem for
China and so on? So there are issues,
very interesting issues there that we
could potentially discuss in a future
geo strategy episode or Indian interest
episode. Uh but overall yes when it
comes to India, China and the US CI2i
and Pakistan is their common asset, the
common vasal, more of a US vasal, less
of a Chinese vasal, but in the past it's
been a full-fledged Chinese vasal.
Pakistan and so on.
Um, Malik said, Colonel Douglas
McGregor, a former adviser to Trump,
says that Israel most likely
underestimated
the the Iranian missile capabilities and
they had to forcefully deescalate or
they would have collapsed internally.
What are my thoughts?
You know, okay, I'm not aware of what he
has said, but uh, thinking about this
logically, it makes makes a makes a bit
of sense actually.
uh it is very likely that Iran has
significant
reserves a significant stockpile of
various kinds of missiles. They have
been very accurately acutely aware of
the fact that they have been encircled
by US bases right to a large extent and
they are aware that most of the nations
in the region are pro- US. They're also
aware of the fact that Israel sees Iran
for good reasons as a as
a major threat, right? So, Iran has been
for a long time aware of the threat uh
of of the of the threat scenario it
faces and that's why it has been
stockpiling missiles of various kinds,
ballistic missiles, cruise missiles,
lots and lots of drones. It's also been
exporting drones to Russia for use in
the Ukraine conflict and so on. So it is
very likely that is that Iran had
tremendous had a tremendous has a has a
tremendous stockpile of missiles and
drones and it most likely significantly
outnumbers the number of Iron Dome
missiles the the Israelis have for the
protection. So it just becomes a
numerical certainty that after a certain
time all Iranian missiles will hit I
will hit hit Israel because their iron
dome missiles will be depleted. Right.
Uh so it is perhaps likely it is perhaps
possible that Israel may have
underestimated
Iran's new uh missile capabilities
and that's why they may have chosen to
deescalate otherwise their military
objectives have not been achieved.
Netanyahu wanted denuclearization of
Iran hasn't happened. He wanted regime
change in Iran hasn't happened. He
wanted a complete comprehensive military
defeat of Iran hasn't happened. None of
that has happened but he had to
deescalate. So there are multiple
factors that must have gone into the
deescalation. Trump also is a big
factor. He wanted he looks like he was
he wanted this to end without an Israeli
victory. Looks like he was okay with
Iran,
you know, pulling out its nuclear
materials from the from the from the
sites that he struck at and so on. So
yeah, it's complicated. But overall, I
would agree that Iran that Israel would
have been in deep trouble if this
conflict had continued and Iran would
have been forced to push it further. I'm
not sure if they would have collapsed
internally. They would have possibly
come close to collapsing. But then they
always have the Sam Samsung option which
is something uh nobody wants to
countenance.
Okay. Um
let's see what other questions do we
have.
Geopolitical dub says what makes gravity
in invisible to arise what is stronger
time or gravity. Okay
well when it comes to gravity well if
you look at it we can look at it from
various perspectives. U if you look at
the Newtonian perspective on on gravity
according to the Newtonian perspective
gravity is an action at a distance kind
of force. it acts at a distance, it acts
instantaneously.
Um, but that's not the case because
Einstein's theory of general relative
relativity shows that there's a speed,
there's an inbuilt speed limit in
gravity, which is the speed of light.
And if you study general relativity, it
tells you that gravity is not a force.
It is something that results from the
curvature of spaceime. So the curvature,
so so spaceime is a four-dimensional
fabric which includes the dimension of
time. Okay. So time is part of the
fabric of spacetime. It's the fourth
dimension. And the presence of mass
causes spacetime to curve. Mass curves
spacetime. And the curvature of
spacetime tells mass how to move. That
is general relativity. And it's it's a
supremely well- tested theory. People
have been trying to break it through
experimental uh tests for decades. never
happened. It's extremely uh well tested.
So general relativity is is the best
theory that we have and it's a very
precise very accurate theory. GPS won't
work without general relativity.
So according to general relativity time
time is a dimension.
It's one of the four dimensions and
gravity the force what we feel is the
force of gravity. It is simply caused by
the curvature of spacetime which we
perceive as a force but it's not really
a force. Okay.
So that is the deal. Um now obviously
the gravity gravity which we feel is a
force does have a strength and it's
extremely extremely strong weak. It's
the weakest of the forces and there also
the possibility that gravity could be
quantum mechanical in nature which to
prove that you to quantize you to
quantize general relativity and that's
not working out for us right so uh the
point is that time is time doesn't have
a strength time is a dimension just like
length or breadth doesn't have a
strength that way time doesn't have a
strength okay so you can't compare the
strength of time versus something else
Time is just a dimension. Uh what makes
gravity invisible to the eyes? Well,
gravity is the curvature of this
four-dimensional fabric of spacetime.
And we cannot perceive four dimensions.
We only perceive three dimensions.
Right? We do perceive electromagnetic
quanta which are photons. That is how we
see the universe. You can see different
colors over here. You can see greenish
blue over here. You can see yellow over
here. Another yellow here. reddish
magenta stuff here and so on. Over here
it's more red. Over here it's blue and
so on. So these are photons of different
frequencies or wavelengths that we are
perceiving in real time. When it comes
to gravity if gravity is has a quantum
mechanical nature it may the fundamental
particle may be the graviton but we
don't perceive it. We are
electromagnetic creatures. We are not
gravitational creatures. We do feel
gravity weakly but our sense organs are
geared towards
the electromagnetic spectrum not the
gravitational spectrum and that's why
gravity is invisible to arise. In case
we have dark matter creatures somewhere
maybe there are dark matter scientists
who are observing this right now and we
not aware of them. Well, if there are
beings made of dark matter only then
their eyes would be gravitational in
nature and they would see the universe
in a whole different set of frequencies
and wavelengths. they would see the
gravitational nature of the universe not
the electromagnetic nature of the
universe. So yeah, I hope that answers
the question. Um Shri Raachandraaya
Namaha says why is the interior of the
earth moving? What if it stops moving?
It's a great question. These are the
kind of questions we should be allowed
to ask. These are the kind of questions
children should be allowed to ask their
teachers in school because that's how
you understand the world. So why is the
interior of the earth moving? It's
because so so it all all goes back to
the beginning of the solar system. How
did the solar system form? The solar
system formed out of a gigantic cloud of
gas and dust. This cloud of gas and dust
was formed by the death of a previous
star which probably went supernova.
Boom. And it just spilled its guts out.
And this gave rise to this gigantic
nebula, this huge cloud of gas and dust.
And after millions, hundreds of millions
of years, this cloud of gas and dust
again coalesed together because of
self-gravitation
and it formed what we call a
protostellar disc. What does a
protostellar disc look like? Let's find
out together. Protostellar disc.
Proto
stellar
disc.
Okay, you can also call it a proto
protolanetary disc. So this is what it
looks like. So eventually because of the
action of its own gravity
self-gravitation
the disc start the the cloud coaleses
into a disc and it develops a a chunkier
more massive center and the rest of the
cloud starts revolving around the center
and over time because of self
gravitation the central component of the
cloud it accumulates enough gas mainly
hydrogen for nuclear fusion to ignite
and that is the birth of a new star and
then over time various
other parts of the of the cloud start
coaling together in the form of planets
and that's what happened in the early
solar system. So initially the earth was
formed about 4.5 or so billion years ago
as a gigantic
as a gigantically hot ball of magma just
molten rock. Okay, it was hugely hot. So
hot that rock would melt and slowly it
cooled slowly. So the cooling happened
on the surface. So it developed a crust,
an outer crust which solidified over
time. But the interior retained the
original heat of the early solar system
and the interior is still molten and at
the core because of pressure there is a
solid core of iron and nickel.
So because of the molten internal
structure of the planet and because of
the angular momentum it inherited from
the beginning of the solar system it's
still moving inside.
That's why the interior of the earth is
moving. I hope it makes sense what I've
explained. What if it stops moving? Well
if it stops moving earth becomes like
Mars.
So Mars is Mars is a much smaller planet
planet than us than than the Earth and
it has its interior has most likely more
or less stopped moving because it has
cooled down. It is mostly solidified.
What does that do? What effect did it
have on Mars? The effect it had on Mars
was that Mars lost
its magnetic field. See moving charges
cause magnetic fields and ions ions
inside the the moving interior of the
earth in the magma layer they cause this
gigantically powerful magnetic field
that the earth has because of the
magnetic field most of the cosmic rays
and much of the solar wind is trapped by
the magnetic field it doesn't reach us
otherwise it will kill us or cause
cancer right and that's why we have been
able to evolve as a species so if the if
the The interior of the earth stops
moving, our magnetic field dies and we
are exposed to horrific
cosmic rays, cosmic radiation, solar
radiation. It will kill us off. That's
what happens.
Okay. Akshit says NATO NATO countries
have together decided to raise their
military budget from 2% to 5% by 2035.
What are the their long-term and
short-term ambitions and future goals?
You see NATO the NATO nations were very
happy to have military budgets that were
less than 2% of their GDP. Because of
that, these nations were able to become
essentially welfare states and they were
able to become super prosperous and and
so on. Very great standards of living
and so on and very lazy compared to the
US very lazy lifestyles.
In if you go to Italy,
people in the afternoon go to sleep for
an hour or two. It's called the siesta
and uh you don't work beyond five and
you don't work you know you don't do
extra shifts and whatnot. People have a
very relaxed lifestyle in Europe. It's
because the government was able to spend
so much more because of its tiny
military budgets. Uh because the US
would the US historically footed most of
the military budget of NATO.
And now Mr. Trump has decided that this
will not happen anymore. and he has said
that NATO nations must raise their
military budgets from below 2% to 5%.
And Mr. Trump has made them agree. The
US is all powerful. So that's why the
NATO nations have decided to to agree to
what Mr. Trump has demanded and they
have they're going to raise their
military budget gradually to 5% by 2035
or so. So the long-term ambition is that
NATO nations must become self-sufficient
in military uh in their military
department and the the spectre that is
given is the spectre of a future Russian
invasion of Europe. Right? So I don't
think Russia has any such ambitions but
okay if it makes you makes you do it do
it. So overall it's the US that wants to
reduce its spending on NATO. It wants
the NATO nations to foot more of the
bill that it was footing earlier. So
that's why it has happened. And
long-term as as a long-term reason for
this, the Russian threat is cited.
Okay. Um
uh Sumit says, "W how would you rank the
Sukoy 57's performance in the Russia
Ukraine war? Many people around the
world have questioned its ability as a
stealth capacity capability. How would
you rank the ba best fighter jets in the
world? I would rank the F22 as the
world's best fighter jet
after that I'm not sure but the F22 is
brilliant and that's why the US doesn't
export it to anybody not even to its
closest vasals right. Uh the Sukai 57's
performance in the in the Russia Ukraine
war I'm not sure how it's performed. Has
it performed at all? I mean has it been
deployed at all? maybe briefly, but it
doesn't look like it's been deployed a
lot. So, I can't really, you know, form
an opinion based on the little that I
know. Uh, now a lot of people have
questioned the Sukoy 57's stealth
capabilities and all that. Many of those
would be from the west because they want
to sell their own planes, their own
fighter aircraft to other countries. Uh,
but it may be that it does have some
deficiencies when it comes to its
stealth profile, which is okay. which is
okay. Look, when it comes to India and
making a decision as to which aircraft
to buy in the interim until we develop
our own AMCA,
uh when it comes to that question, we
need to be practical and pragmatic. We
don't want to spend a$100 million plus
dollars per piece. Okay? We can't afford
to spend that much. And secondly, we
can't afford to have an aircraft that
has inbuilt loopholes, inbuilt
uh inbuilt back doors and kill switches.
That's the F-35. We can't afford to have
that. That will compromise us no end.
And thirdly, you the fighter plane you
purchase doesn't have to be the best in
the world. It has to be decent.
As long as it has fifth generation
capabilities which the Suka 57 has, I
think we should consider it seriously.
Even if it doesn't have a super stealthy
profile, it's okay, right? Because at
the end of the day, quantity has a
quality of its own. Get a 100 200 of
these and you know it'll be a game
changer. So that's uh how I would see
this.
Uh
Amisha says, "Is the moon slowly moving
away from the earth? Is this true?" It
is true it's moving away fractionally
from the earth. So uh in the past let's
say when the earth was a billion years
old or so the moon was much much closer
to the earth and the earth's rotation
period was also much faster. So the so
the earth day was about 10 hours or so.
One day on on our planet was 10 10 hours
only. Now it's 24 hours right? Roughly
24 hours. In the past it was about 10
hours and the moon was much closer to
the earth and the moon has been slowly
gradually maybe a centimeter or so per
year around around that kind of figure
it's moving away from earth because of
of gravitational dynamics. Uh and the
moon is tidily locked with the planet
with our earth but in maybe a 100
million years maybe 100 million years
the moon will have receded sufficiently
from the earth for solar eclipses to
never be full in the in the future. So
right now we we have we sometimes have
complete solar eclipses, right? When the
where the sun is completely blocked out
by the moon. In the future it won't be
full or complete solar eclipses. There
will only be partial solar eclipses and
you will have annular solar eclipses
which means that the sun is not fully
blocked by the moon and there's a ring
around the moon when the moon moves away
sufficiently. So in about 100 million
years the moon will be sufficiently far
away for solar eclipses to no longer be
complete solar eclipses. So it is moving
away from the earth for sure and the
rotation period of the earth is also
slowing down correspondingly. So in the
future the the earth will have a 25-hour
day and more in the future.
Uh
what else do we have?
Okay. Shaswat Wenut says, "What's your
opinion on India's neutral stand in this
whole Iran Israel conflict?" I
completely agree with India's neutral
stand in this conflict.
This is not our war.
There is no reason whatsoever for India
to take sides in this war. Look,
we have an excellent relationship with
Israel. No question. We have significant
technological cooperation. We have
significant defense cooperation. Uh we
manufacture Israeli drones in India. The
Harop drone which was used to uh attack
which was used to uh strike Pakistani
terrorist infrastructure in May. That
that harop drone is built in India by
Adani right it's an Israeli designed
drone. So we have a lot of cooperation
u between India and Israel. A very good
working relationship. We have some
issues also but overall it's a very
positive and excellent relationship. On
the other hand when it comes to Iran we
also have a reasonably good
relationship. We have no significant
uh areas of divergence. Once in a while
some Iranian politician will make make
statements about Kashmir which is
annoying but it's only verbal
statements. Uh Iran doesn't actually
take any real actions that would be
detrimental to India's interests. Right.
Israel does not Iran does not have a
friendly relationship with Pakistan
because Pakistan is a US vasal and
there's also the Sunnishia issue and so
on. So that is good for us right because
Pakistan is a terrorist nation our
number one or number two enemy and not
because of us because of them they seek
to destroy us right so and and in the
past we've had energy cooperation much
more with Iran
so we and Iran has given us access to
the Chabahar port through which we can
access Afghanistan and central Asia as
well so overall it's a good relationship
that we have with Iran and the US has
has tried its best to to you know
visiate the relationship. They they have
pressurized India to stop buying oil
from Iran which has put Iran under
pressure and they've had to seek out
other other partners like China etc.
Right?
So overall we have good relations with
Israel as well as Iran and it makes
sense for us to not
divert you know not move away from a
neutral stance in this matter and we
have exhorted both nations to settle
their differences on the negotiating
table and don't fight don't use military
means that's what our stand has been and
I completely agree with this that.
Okay. Um,
okay. Let's see some other questions.
Um,
okay. I have to hunt for good questions
now. Okay, let's take this one. Um, mind
your own business says, "Why talk about
China or US Bangladesh as a vasal? Why
not India making Bangladesh aal or why
doesn't Bangladesh offer itself to India
like it did to China? Well, you see when
you grow up you realize it's not that
easy and that simple.
Okay,
we can talk all we want.
We can talk all we want but the real
world it doesn't operate on the basis of
verbal talk talk. It operates on the
basis of ground realities.
ground realities and the basic ground
reality is hard power.
Okay. So yeah, we can say why not India
making Bangladesh aal
but what if there are way more powerful
nations which will not allow this to
happen.
Right? You have to understand a bit of
nuance and complexity.
If you just do surface level analysis
your whole life, you will never
understand anything and you will keep
asking these questions. Why talk like
this? Why not talk like that?
Hind the world doesn't work like that.
You may be as patriotic as we want but
you have to you have to acknowledge
the ground realities of the world. What
are the ground realities?
Bangladesh was cooperating with India
for about 20 years for more than 10
years as long as Shik Hassina was prime
minister. Bangladesh was not an Indian
vasal but it was not a Chinese and not a
not a US vasal. Bangladesh was very
cooperative with India and that was a
great victory for our foreign policy.
Then what the US did? What the US did?
See now you'll ask yourself why does the
US how can the US do something in
Bangladesh? The US is so far away. Ask
yourself this question. If the US is so
far away and China is so powerful, why
can't it take Taiwan?
It's because the US is so powerful that
even in China's own backyard, China
can't take an island. That's how
powerful the US is. So what the US did
in Bangladesh is that they effected a
regime change operation
and they got rid of Shikh Hassina and
implanted
a puppet government, the Muhammad Yunus
regime, which is actually a military
government. Okay, the military is
running the country. Muhammad Yunus is
just the puppet, the show, the face for
show. And when the US makes a nation of
Assal, India has to stay out of it
otherwise there'll be tremendous
repercussions that you can't imagine.
So and obviously the US must have given
a lot of very sweet inducements to the
Bangladesh military to Muhammad Yunus
etc. the kind of inducements India can't
afford to give because we don't have
deep enough pockets like the US has.
All right. So please understand these
are the some of the ground realities.
The world doesn't work on the basis of
slogans. We can say whatever we want but
what we do is always commensurate with
our hard power and it's always in in
measured against the hard power of our
adversaries.
That's how it works.
All right.
Mahesta says um
does a leader seek to lead or is he
called called to it? Well, sometimes
leaders seek to lead because they know
they have this leadership potential
capabilities or whatever and sometimes
leaders are called to lead even though
they don't want to lead. I mean since we
have been discussing Iran Israel I mean
when let's talk about Iran and the
current Supreme Leader of Iran Mr. uh
Kami.
So Mr. Kamei came to power after ayati
died. I don't remember which year it
was. Sometime in the 1990s was it? Let
me see. Let's let's quickly
um
find out
Kmeni. So he passed away in 1989
and that is when Mr. Ali Kame became the
supreme leader of Iran. Now Mr. Ali Kame
did not want to be the supreme leader of
Iran. He strongly essentially protested
I don't want to be the guy. I'm not the
right guy for you and so on. But the
Iranian majalis or whatever it's called,
they decided you're going to be the guy.
And he has been the supreme leader ever
since. Sometimes you don't want it but
you're called to it. But in some cases
you want it, you seek it and you gain
it. For example, Mr. Trump. Mr. Trump
decided he wanted to become the
president and he put his own money into
the campaign and he succeeded twice. So
here you have a leader who has sought
the supreme position. He has sought to
lead. On the other hand, if you look at
Iran, Mr. Kame never wanted to lead but
here here he is as a supreme leader. So
two examples which kind of illustrate
the point.
Okay. Um,
okay. Krishna Nak says, "Do you think
the Gulf Cooperation Council countries
are really standing with Iran or are the
secretly happy that Israel attacked
Iran?" Uh, when it comes to the Gulf,
Gulf nations, the Arab nations. Okay,
let's take a look at the map. Uh, which
will help us um understand the region a
little better. A little better. So, look
at the Gulf region, West Asia. So what
we have here is Iran in the east and
then we have all the Arab nations Oman,
Yemen, Saudi Arabia, Kuwait, Iraq,
Syria, Jordan and Egypt is also an Arab
nation. Right? So that's the situation.
So you have
Iran which is a non-Arab nation. It's an
Aryan nation essentially. It's an
extension of the Indian subcontinent.
And you have all these other nations,
Arabic nations. Um and the GCC nations
are mainly the Arab nations. Iran is a
Shia nation. All the GCC other nations
in the GCC are Sunni nations and u Iran
is is a nation that has historically
ambitions of its own geopolitical
ambitions and so on. U and the Arab
nations kind of fear Iran, right? And
there is rivalry between between Iran
and Saudi Arabia uh and also Turkey to
some extent for the leadership of the
Islamic world. so on mult it's it's it's
complicated multiple levels to this
thing
so and and recently in 2020
you had the signing of the Abraham
Accords Accords I think it was in 2020
Mr. Mr. Trump presided over that and
that brought forth some kind of
normalization relations between Israel
and and and some of these Arab nations
and what the Arab nations want for
example what the UAE wants and desires
is stability in the region they don't
want warfare what Saudi Arabia also
wants is stability in the region they
don't want warfare they don't want
destabilized neighborhood they want a
stable neighborhood so that they can
work towards development
They want economic development. They
want to develop their nations further.
They understand that, you know, oil is
no longer going to be forever the the
commodity that the world uh prizes over
everything else. You're going to have
changes in technology. You're going to
have the advent of the electric vehicle
era, lithium era, and so on. So, you
can't keep depending on oil forever. So,
they're trying to diversify uh their e
economies and so on. And they they want
to develop the region further. So they
don't want warfare.
So I'm sure many of these nations are
not happy that Israel attacked Iran
because that destabilizes the
neighborhood.
And I'm not sure they all stand with
Iran. They neither stand with Iran nor
are they happy that the Israeli attack
caused the destabilization of the
region. I mean flights were diverted. I
have people asking me is it is it safe
to go to the UK today and so on. Right?
So uh
so these nations are not secretly happy
about what has happened and then and
they don't even stand with Iran. They
actually want to be left alone. They
want to be left alone to to develop
their economies further and and so on.
So that's the deal.
Uh
Susan says um as per Chava index 2024
USA's hard power score is 93.32 India
has 4.91. What weapon technologies does
the US have that India lacks? Is it just
better quantity? What American missile/
technology do we have no answer to? The
US overall is a superpower in every
sense.
uh we have excellent missiles but as as
far as I know we haven't announced
interbalistic uh intercontinental
capabilities of the AGI 5 or or
something beyond that. So that's one
capability we kind of lack. Uh I think
the the longest range stated ranged or
announced range is about 8,000
kilometers or so of the AGN 5. Maybe we
are understating the range of the Agnifi
just not to so so as to not to offend or
alarm
nations like the US right but maybe
that's one thing we lack okay one one
example of a thing we lack otherwise our
missiles are supremely
good we have some of the best missiles
in the world when it comes to aircraft
the US has far better aircraft the US
has strategic bombers we lack that right
the US has all kinds of whole families
of fighter planes we lack that the US
has these heavy, massively heavy
transport aircraft, we lack that. Um,
the US has extraordinarily good nuclear
submarines, we don't have that. And so
on and so forth. I could go on forever.
So the US is far ahead of India. Way
ahead of India. Okay.
So it's quantity as well as quality.
It's it's way higher in both in both
considerations. Okay. Uh for India to to
increase its hard power score, first of
all, we need to reduce. So right now one
of the factors that that affects our
hard power score and brings it down is
our um is the fact that we are not
self-sufficient in energy. We have to
import about 59%
of our energy as far as I remember or
maybe around whatever but about half or
more of our energy has to be imported
that is a critical problem for India.
It's an Achilles heel for India. We have
to find our own energy resources somehow
or the other. If we can do that, that
that will bring our hard hard power
score higher. U another factor that that
brings our hard power score down is that
we allegedly officially have only only
about 150 of 16 nuclear warheads. The
Americans have thousands, right? So
that's a huge factor that brings our
hard power score down. Uh another factor
that brings our hard power score down is
our lack of power projection
capabilities. The Americans have
tremendous power projection
capabilities. We have very limited power
projection capabilities. So all of these
factors put together. And then there's
the economic factor.
There's the uh GDP factor. The US GDP is
way ahead of India. That's a huge factor
that brings our hard power score down.
Our limited military budget also brings
our hard power score down and so on and
so forth. So that's why our hard power
score is 4.91 and the US is 93 almost
94. Right.
Okay. Let's take some more questions. Um
uh Rishab Shuklas says updates on ISRO's
Gaganyan mission and other missions such
as developing reusable rockets. I'll
have to speak to somebody from ISRO. I'm
not sure about what's the deal with the
Gagyan mission. Um, we were actually
supposed to do the first uh launches
last year, but I think there there were
delays because of COVID and so on. There
may be delays because of technical
issues. I'm not sure. As far as I know,
we're supposed to do at least the first
launch, unmanned launch this year with
the uh heaviest rocket, the most
powerful rocket that we have, the LMB,
whatever. It used to be called the GSLV
in the past. So, as far as I know,
there's supposed to be a launch this
year, but I'm not sure what the status
is on that. Uh, reusable rockets, I have
absolutely no idea. I would be I would
be thrilled if I is rover to be
developing reusable rockets. I I want
nothing more than that. I mean, there's
nothing more that I want than I is
developing reusable rockets, but are we
doing that? If yes, what the what is the
status? I am not quite sure. So yeah,
I'm not quite sure what what what the
deal is, what's happening, what the
status is.
Okay, Draj Kamat says, "If Israel is not
a US, then the entirety then is the
entirety of the West an Israeli." Sounds
a bit far-fetched. They are basically
the source sole superpower, then why
didn't the US help Israel during the
six- day war? Well, it's a historical
conflict. That's that's an old issue.
The question is, you had a 12-day war
just now. Mr. Trump has formally
declared that this war will be called
the 12-day war. So, it's now to be
called the 12-day war. So, we had a
12-day war just now. And the US did not
really help Israel achieve a complete
victory. The US did not help Mr.
Netanyahu achieve his heart's desire,
which was the denuclearization of Iran,
a military defeat of Iran, and the
regime change in Thran. None of this
happened. So, Mr. Netanyahu has not
achieved what he wanted.
But does it mean Israel has not achieved
what he wanted? Maybe Israel is fine but
Netanyahu isn't happy. H now the
question is that is which who is whose W
was right? The US generally has vasals
all over the world. Pakistan east and
west Pakistan are examples. Japan is
occupied. South Korea is occupied.
Germany and Italia are occupied vasals.
Various other NATO nations are
nonoccupied vasals but vasals by by the
fact that they are part of NATO EU
nations of vasals and so on so forth
the question is Israel what is the
status of Israel is Israel a US vasal
state
well it doesn't look like Israel is a US
US vasal state because the US doesn't
extract a pound of flesh from Israel
like it does from every other nation
on the other hand the US does give a few
pounds of flesh to Israel whenever
Israel leads that. So then the question
is, is the US an Israeli vasal? That's
some what some people claim. Well, I
think I will reserve my judgment until I
find more information.
Okay.
All right. Um,
what else? Okay, let us take this one.
Anonymous scientist says, "Can India
purchase P from Pakistan by giving some
money? Would that be acceptable to
Indians and would Pakistan accept that
offer?" You know what? If the Indian
government offers some a certain amount
of money to Pakistan and Pakistan
accepts that offer, I'll be fine with
that. I'll be okay with it. Fine.
I'm sure many Indians will be okay with
it. But many Indians may also say that
why why buy it with our with money? It's
our territory.
Yeah. And maybe that's a just that's a
good argument perhaps, right? Uh but if
you can do a one-time payment and get
rid of the problem, maybe it's worth it.
So maybe there are two sides of the
coin. But you know the real question is
would Pakistan accept that offer? And
the answer is no. Because Pakistan has
masters who have deeper pockets and
Pakistan has masters
who need Pakistan to retain the
territory.
These masters essentially it's the US
and to some extent China mainly the US.
They they seek to use they have always
sought to use Pakistan as as a factor
that destabilizes India. It's
counterbalance to India. The US funded
and financed Pakistani terrorism against
India for decades. It's a well-known
fact, right? So Pakistan is val valuable
and PK is also valuable. Why give away
an inch of territory to the nation you
want to destabilize? So it won't happen
and Pakistan even if it wants won't be
allowed to accept such an offer.
Um
let us see what else we have. Um,
okay. No,
science dates the earth at 4.54 billion
years. Hinduism says Brahma's day is
4.32 billion years. I'm not sure what
Hinduism says. Okay. There are various
interpretations of what one lifetime of
Brahma is in one day, one day of Brahma
is. So there are, see, for example, if
you look at the worst website of all
time, which is Wikipedia. Let's just
briefly take a look at that just for
illustrative purposes. never rely on
Wikipedia information but I'm just
taking a look at okay so Hindu cosmology
Wikipedia Wikipedia
okay Hindu cosmology so what does
Wikipedia have to say about this yeah
Hindu cosmology and tremendous huge
numbers and stuff do we have something
Oops it's gone
um what do we have locas multiple
universes Brahmandanda
Brahmandanda cosmic egg uh
uh okay I'm not sure which article it
was I had seen in the past some article
in which you have these time timelines
called Hindu units of time let's take a
look at this maybe this okay so you have
various units
uh cedurial units suranta
small units of time used in the Vedas
cosmic metrics Maha kalpa
which is 100 years of Brahma.
So kalpa is what 12 hours of Brahma
which is 4.3 billion years for humans.
Okay. According to Wikipedia I think
that's what you have found from
Wikipedia. So according to Wikipedia one
kalpa
apparently is equivalent to 12 hours of
Brahma's lifetime and that's 4.3 billion
years. So one full day of Brahma's
lifetime according to this information
here here here would be 8.6 billion
years.
I'm not sure if it's a precise match or
whatever. I I don't know. And I'm not
sure what it hints or what it doesn't
hint. So yeah, I'm I I'm not the guy to
ask these questions. Okay. I'm not an
expert by any means on on on sadly our
our scriptures and all. And yeah.
Okay.
Um, Amisha says, "Trump has now become a
meme. He has lost credibility." Well,
kind of. Well, he's a funny guy. He
Nobody can speak the way Mr. Trump can
speak, right? He has his own way of
speaking. It's very hard to imitate
that. And he even writes the way he
tweets. Uh, the way he speaks. He tweets
the way he speaks. So, he's kind of a
meme. He he has a ponch for making very
very very very memew worthy statements
and remarks and he did that in the wake
in the wake of the uh violation of the
ceasefire between Israel and Iran right
he was very very upset and so on but has
he lost credibility
I'm not sure if he has lost credibility
he seems to have actually for a change
uh enforce a ceasefire when it comes to
India Pakist an he claimed to have
mediated but it was not true but when it
comes to Israel Iran it looks like he
has actually actively participated from
day one and he has put an end to the
fighting and uh you know if he can
manage if he can pull off a Nobel Peace
Prize it will build bring him way more
credibility so I think it's somewhere in
between yes people don't take Trump as
seriously as they would take other past
US presidents partly because of Mr.
Trump's personality and all but Trump
does mean business and uh well if he
makes a threat people take it very
seriously. I I promise you that if he
makes a threat against India we have to
take it seriously. It's clear that he
made Mr. Netanyahu agree to a ceasefire.
I'm not sure how he pursued Mr.
Netanyahu but he did pursue it Mr.
Netanyahu and it looks like Mr.
Netanyahu was not happy with it. So
Trump when he makes when he wants to get
certain things done he does get those
those things done. So that would
actually mean that you have to take him
seriously which means that he still has
credibility. Of course there is reason
to what you say but I would say that he
has not entirely lost credibility.
Okay.
Uh let's take a couple more questions
maybe. Saria saids maybe the US doesn't
want to denuclearize Iran to sell
weapons to the Middle East. It is
already selling weapons to the Middle
East. Uh they recently concluded a
gigantic ginormous deal with Saudi
Arabia. More than a I don't know
I don't know $100 billion. I'm not sure
what it was. A huge deal with Saudi
Arabia. Let's quickly take a look at
what was the uh kind of deal they did
with Saudi Arabia. Huge weapons deal. So
they don't need the war to go on for
that. US Saudi
Saudi weapons deal. Trump.
Okay. not 2017 brah. Okay. $142 billion
sale. That's a gigantic deal. And Saudi
Arabia, this agreement with Saudi Arabia
includes investments in weapons and
technology totaling 600 billion. And the
outright sale is $142 billion. That's a
gigantic sale for Donald Trump and for
the US. So Saudi Arabia is anyway, the
Middle East countries are anyway buying
US weapons in large large large
quantities, keeping Mr. Trump happy and
so on. Um
so that is already there and this
happened before the the Israel Iran war
before Israel attacked Iran. So um I
think what the US wants is to maintain
the current balance of power in the
region. They don't want to create a
vacuum where Iran exists today as of
now. That's what it looks like. And let
us take maybe one more question. Um
okay let's see. Um
um Yash says India does India have the
potential to become a major defense
exporter in the world? It does. India
does have the potential for that. India
does very much have that. We have the
recent operation Synindhur showed us how
powerful, how accurate, how excellent
our indigenously designed and developed
and manufactured weapons systems are.
Yeah.
Krishna Ragunat says, "If the partition
of India had never happened, this is the
final question for the day by the way.
Uh, if the partition of India had never
happened, would India be in a better or
worse state than the current political
situations that India has with Pakistan
and Bangladesh?" Well, it could have
been better, it could could have been
worse. On the one hand, you would have a
very mixed population in India, a
significantly higher Muslim population
in India and allegedly Muslims can't
stay with Hindus. That's the two nation
theory put forth by Jina and and his his
his buddies, right? So if so it would
all have depended on the leadership that
India would have had in this in this
hypothetical scenario. If India in a
hypothetical scenar scenario was never
partitioned but had weak leadership then
it would it would have caused chaos
maybe religious strife
ongoing religious strife terrible
religious strife but if India had a
strong leadership maybe somebody like
Subbashra was ruling for 20 years or
more then he would have ruled with an
iron hand and would would have never
allowed that sort of religious strife to
happen and he would have never allowed
uh extremist and fundamentalist elements
to thrive he would have crushed them
all. So it depends right so one could
put forth various scenarios just like
one does for future uh forecasting.
Okay with that we have come to the end
of today's session. Thank you so much
for the questions and I will see you in
I'll see you on Friday Indian interest
8:00 p.m. After that we're going to have
another ask a budget session. So thank
you so much for the questions. Keep
asking your questions. Keep learning,
keep being inquisitive, keep raising
your standards, and I thank you for your
viewership, for the questions. And I'll
see you on Friday. Thank you so much.